<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://v-azza.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://v-azza.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-05-22T16:32:23+00:00</updated><id>https://v-azza.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>A simple, whitespace theme for academics. Based on [*folio](https://github.com/bogoli/-folio) design. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">thinkpads galore and my shift to Linux computing</title><link href="https://v-azza.github.io/blog/2025/thinkpad/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="thinkpads galore and my shift to Linux computing"/><published>2025-02-19T12:39:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-19T12:39:00+00:00</updated><id>https://v-azza.github.io/blog/2025/thinkpad</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://v-azza.github.io/blog/2025/thinkpad/"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve recently bought myself my second Thinkpad. I’ve been daily driving a Lenovo Thinkpad X1 Carbon Gen 10 with Linux for almost 2 years now. It has served me very well and in this blog post, I discuss how this family of machines has fit into my productive working schedule, and any project work that I have been doing alongside this.</p> <h3 id="1-my-first-thinkpad-and-why-ive-decided-to-use-this-machine">1. My first Thinkpad, and why I’ve decided to use this machine</h3> <p>Around the same time I bought my first personal productivity/learning-focused Thinkpad X1 Carbon Gen 10, I was using a Macbook Pro M2 for work. What I really liked about my Macbook was the battery life, the ease of use of MacOS, the build quality, and the all-aluminium chassis. When I was issued that as a company device, I admired the simplicity of that machine, and how everything ‘just worked’. In hindsight, I admit a large portion of that is down to the OS that on the machine and less do with the hardware. All this doesn’t mean that the laptop is perfect by any stretch.</p> <p>Because of my shoes or clothing, I often found myself being statically shocked while I was in the office and I touched the aluminium chassis of the laptop. I found that to be very annoying, but not a deal breaker. In my current role - we are issued laptops with an all-aluminium body and I often find myself shocking myself on the chassis after long walks in the office. Another thing was that the RAM that was issued to all staff members for these Macs were woefully inadequate. It was only 8 GB. This seemed to be okay for most users in that business, but later in that role I got interested in development and the RAM amount just wasn’t okay. My web browser is also full of open tabs, and found that my machine slowed down when I had my web browser open, I also found running most virtual machines outside lightweight Linux distrutions a hard task.</p> <p>So to develop my own tools, projects and general productivity - I found myself in the market for a new machine at the time. I had a think about some of the things I really enjoyed about my work’s Mac M2, and the things I want to achieve with a new project machine:</p> <ol> <li>I wanted to get decent at using and administering Linux machines, for the purposes of taking the CompTIA Linux+ exam.</li> <li>I wanted a machine to be thin and light, and portable enough to fit into a bag with plenty of space to spare.</li> <li>The hardware needs to be strong enough to easily last me a few years. I need to be able to run, at a maximum, a Windows virtual machine with 16 GB of dedicated RAM.</li> <li>The build quality needs to be solid, but not nescessarily an all metal/aluminium chassis.</li> </ol> <p>So I bit the bullet and purchased a used Lenovo Thinkpad Gen 10. At the time, I felt that it was the perfect machine for my needs, and once I slapped Linux Mint on it, the puzzle pieces started coming together. However, this would be the first time that I’ve dedicated a whole machine to Linux, and the first time that I would be daily driving Linux in general. In the past, I’ve used Linux in virtual machines for educational purposes only.</p> <p>As most Linux users experience, I immediately ran into problems. Things that seemingly worked perfectly fine in Windows simply did not work in Linux, such as the webcam module and the fingerprint reader. Luckily for me, I never use these functions on my device, nor do I intend to in the future. Fixing these have remained on my personal ‘To do’ list. But these have been at the bottom of my list since, up until this day. I did experience some other problems such as the SIM card slot not working, but these were fixed through some tweaking and searching of Offical drivers. Prior to purchasing the device, I did read that Thinkpads are very Linux-friendly, but I suppose my choice of distribution, coupled with the fact that the drivers for the parts I mention were not packaged as part of the standard build for the OS, are the reasons they don’t work.</p> <p>I only have experienced two main hardware-related issues.</p> <ul> <li>The battery and power-hungry processor: <ul> <li> <p>The battery for a device this age is quite simply, pitiful. I often find myself having to recharge this device. My train into work from Cambridgeshire to London is only around 1 hour 5 minutes and this journey often brings this device from a full charge to below 40%. Coming from a Macbook Pro M2, this was a huge stuggle to deal with at the start. I have investigated and I know what the cause is.</p> </li> <li> <p>This device comes equipped with the notoriously-power hungry 12th Gen Intel i7-1260P processor. It has 12 cores and 16 threads, and it runs at 4.7 GHz. It is great for the tasks I throw at it and the several virtual machines I can now run parallel to each other, but the power consumption is high.</p> </li> <li> <p>I’ve used the upower module in my system, and run <code>upower -i $(upower -e | grep -i BAT)</code>. My device is currently on 221 charge cycles. This is a lot for a laptop and this is also a factor. This module tells me that this device’s battery can hold around 41.97 Wh of energy when full, which is sigificantly less than the designed 57 Wh from new. I am happy to replace the battery once it start to become a serious issue, however I always carry a decent charger with me at all times and it hasn’t become enough of an issue to address.</p> </li> </ul> </li> <li>The trackpad size: <ul> <li>The size of the trackpad is not ideal, it is slightly too small. This issue isn’t nearly bad as the others I’ve mentioned - and I have gotten used to it over time. The palm and touch rejection is not perfect but this also manageable and I have gotten used to it over time.</li> </ul> </li> </ul> <p>In retrospect, both these issues could be down to the fact that I have come from a very compentent and well-built Macbook. It is worth remebering, with all these issues - I still managed to secure this machine for less than half the price of a similarly-specced, used Macbook Pro M1 at the time.</p> <h4 id="but-that-being-said-i-love-this-laptop">But that being said, I love this laptop!</h4> <p>Apart from the issues, in general I love this device. It has been a trusty sidekick when travelling, easily handling my projects and coding projects. It’s also been abroad several times, in places such as Gibraltar, Spain and Sri Lanka. Travelling throughout the UK for work and various other endevours, means that I can carry this laptop with ease. I made sure to get a model that has 32 GB of RAM so I can run my virtual machines with little issues. Sometimes I am able to run multiple VM in parallel to get work done and this is great.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/blog/beach-laptop.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/blog/view.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> <b>Left:</b> The obligatory 'I'm coding on the beach' picture. Beer is optional. <br/><br/> <b>Right:</b> The view I was treated to at the time. Taken in Trincomalee, Sri Lanka. </div> <p>Being a Thinkpad, the keyboard is very nice to type on. I have really enjoyed coding on this device. I have been looking on forums online and I can see that others prefer the older keyboards with greater key travel and more solid feel. I am a user of a custom-built mechanical keyboard for my gaming machine at home and I feel right at home here. The force you need to apply each key to actuate it, is just right. The build quality of this device is good, and I have no concerns about this device holding up to the test of time. It is elegant enough to not feel out of place in formal settings and not garish or flashy enough to stand out in the crowd. I made the right choice in my eyes.</p> <h3 id="2-my-recent-addition">2. My recent addition</h3> <p>After my overall success of adding the X1 Carbon to my toolkit of devices I can rely on, I have decided that I need a Windows-only laptop for calls and online cerification exams. I am doing a lot of my recent certification through Pearson VUE, and after selling an old laptop I had been using for this purpose on Ebay, I needed something to replace it. Pearson VUE online exams uses a very intrusive piece of software for the exams themselves and of course - it is incompatible with Linux natively.</p> <p>The specs are: Intel i5-8350U, Integrated Graphics, 256GB Samsung NVme SSD, 32GB DDR4 3200 RAM. This device should be fine and fit for the purpose I intend to use it for. Upon getting it on my hands for the first time, I can feel that the device is much thicker and heavier than my X1 Carbon. This makes sense, given that the X1 Carbon is the ‘Thin and Light’ range of Thinkpads.</p> <p>The keyboard feels solid and you need much more force to actuate a key when you compare it to the X1 Carbon. I feel like I can drop this from a decent height without it breaking. I can’t really say the same for my coding machine - but they are being used for different purposes.</p> <p>There’s a big community online who really love this particular machine. A lot of the Thinkpad enthusiasts commonly say that the T480 is the ‘last real Thinkpad’ I’m not sure if I can fully agree with that but it does have some of the creature comforts of modern devices, such as two type-c charging ports for charging. It has some ‘nice to haves’ such as a full-sized ethernet port for metwork troubleshooting.</p> <p>I’ve even tried to play some games on it. I’ve played League of Legends on it, and it seems to run fine. The hardware seems to be enough for a laptop in 2025. Things like the inbuilt fingerint reader works in Windows out of the box. I haven’t tried any other OS on this laptop, other than Windows.</p> <p>This laptop has practicality built in. It has two batteries, one externally built-in and one internal. You can get a high-capacity version of the external battery. It’s worth noting at this point that Lenovo and Thinkpads more generally are just more repairable than other brands. It is trivially easy to order offical replacement parts for Lenovo Thinkpads, and the 3rd party market is vast.</p> <p>The only thing I could seriously fault the T480 for, is it’s bezel size around the display. It is too large for my liking, especially towards the bottom of the display towards the hinge. On a less serious note - the T480 is bulky, so you should be ready for that if you plan on travelling with the T480. Generally speaking, the weight and size of the device is manageable for me though.</p> <h3 id="3-conclusions">3. Conclusions</h3> <p>For the price, this laptop is a bargain - and a great way to spec a machine (laptop) for a family member who just needs access to the internet. It is highly repairable and a good bet for something that just works. I’d reccommend the T480 for almost everyone.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="software"/><category term="code"/><category term="hardware"/><category term="tips"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I've recently bought myself my second Thinkpad. Here I talk about why I did this, and why I am now relying on Thinkpads to get my own work done.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">my new and improved personal website</title><link href="https://v-azza.github.io/blog/2024/website/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="my new and improved personal website"/><published>2024-09-22T18:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2024-09-22T18:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://v-azza.github.io/blog/2024/website</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://v-azza.github.io/blog/2024/website/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="my-old-website">My old website</h3> <p>So I was in the need for a personal website overhaul. My old website worked fine and all, and it functioned as expected. However I built it almost entirely myself (and you could tell!). I built the site off Next.js and integrated this on the web development platform <a href="https://www.netlify.com/">Netlify</a>. It worked well for my first foray into web development, and it was beginner friendly in terms of compiling and deploying my code to GihHub automatically. Once I was happy with my changes, all I needed to do was to push my code from VS code using the GitHub remote repositories function.</p> <p>Using Netlify for this basically left me to focus on the the design of the website itself, and the content. However, this intense ‘DIY’ approach of doing things prevented me further developing the site, due to the increases in complexity when I looking to add functionality. For example: adding a dark mode button took me around 80+ lines of code and around 12 hours of figuring things out, to do.</p> <p>I did learn a lot from creating this site, in this state, but given it’s simplicity and difficulty of updating - I have grown out of using it for now. If you would like to see it for yourself, I have it hosted on Netlify’s own infrstracuture, and it is available <a href="https://vazza.netlify.app">here</a>.</p> <div class="row mt-4"> <div class="col-sm mt-4 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/oldwebsite/about.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-4 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/oldwebsite/about-light.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-4 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/oldwebsite/blog.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> <div class="col-sm mt-4 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <img src="/assets/img/oldwebsite/title.jpeg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="lazy" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <div class="caption"> Some screenshots of my old website as of today. They might change in the future to reflect this new site you're looking at, but I have no plans to edit this old site as of yet. </div> <p>As you can see, my old site was very rudimentary. However, it served it’s purpose pretty well. I was able to pick up the basics of HTML again after taking a hiatus from it, since learning it in high school. I learned how to effectively use css to theme a website from scratch and I learnt the basics of Next.js.</p> <h3 id="my-new-website">My new website</h3> <p>I’ve built this website off the back of <a href="https://jekyllrb.com/">Jekyll</a>, upon recommendations from my current manager, who has <a href="https://henrycole.uk/">his own site</a>. I decided to use a modified version of the <a href="https://github.com/alshedivat/al-folio">Al-Folio</a> theme, as this theme met my needs for a simple, easy to use website.</p> <p>Not only does creating my website in this new way reduce the amount of backend work I have to do to keep my website functioning, it allows me to focus 98 to 99% of my attention on this site, on producing the content itself. This is always a good thing in my eyes, as my day job is starting to get more and more demanding.</p> <p>I started by watching some YouTube videos about creating this, and I found <a href="https://youtu.be/g6AJ9qPPoyc?si=RmYr9wfA5YzvFlWa">this video</a> the most helpful.</p> <p>This new method of using Jekyll for my website is much better than using Netlify. This is because before, I felt encouraged to push every change I made to the code no matter how small, or big the change. With the use of Jekyll, you are almost forced to develop locally before pushing. I know that the process of developing locally and pushing once all changes have been made in this way is recommended with the use of Netlify - but I fell into bad habits developing with Netlify, in waiting for the build process to fail to indicate whether I have pushed bad code.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="code"/><category term="me"/><category term="dev"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[the story of how I created this shiny new website]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">music I like</title><link href="https://v-azza.github.io/blog/2024/music/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="music I like"/><published>2024-04-28T18:54:00+00:00</published><updated>2024-04-28T18:54:00+00:00</updated><id>https://v-azza.github.io/blog/2024/music</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://v-azza.github.io/blog/2024/music/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="vibeslofi"><a href="https://open.spotify.com/playlist/0Wmwv2CYB0Qqo2aMbQbZzB?si=ab940b3844164a12">vibes+lofi</a></h2> <p>I like to listen to Lofi when I am programming mostly. I also like to listen to this music when I needing to concentrate on something, given that this playlist is mostly instrumental.</p> <h2 id="stuff"><a href="https://open.spotify.com/playlist/0uz554cDJDvguSWdq11DfO?si=10d41f57144a4b4d">stuff</a></h2> <p>A mishmash of mostly rock music that I like to listen to when I am working with my hands. I usually listen to this when I am working on my electronics projects, or cleaning my car.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="me"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This blog entry will link you to some music I like. The majority of the music I listen to is on Spotify.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">working in a SOC - My experiences and takeaways</title><link href="https://v-azza.github.io/blog/2024/soc/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="working in a SOC - My experiences and takeaways"/><published>2024-02-12T11:12:10+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-12T11:12:10+00:00</updated><id>https://v-azza.github.io/blog/2024/soc</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://v-azza.github.io/blog/2024/soc/"><![CDATA[<p>I have now worked in a SOC for almost 2 years and I have learned a huge amount. Having come from a job role that was consultancy-based, and not nearly as technical as a SOC role demands - I felt that the learning curve was very steep when I first started working in this role. I not only had to take on a lot of new skills, I also had to hone and apply a lot of the skills I already know to practial scenarios and situations where clients are being infected with ransomware for example.</p> <p>This section will go through some of my thoughts and feelings regarding working in a SOC and a ‘SOC-as-a-service’ capability, that my employer provides for their clients. I will go through what I mean by a ‘SOC-as-a-service’ and what this means to my larger Cyber Security role.</p> <p>What is a SOC? What is a SOC-as-a-service?</p> <p>A SOC (Security Operations Centre), usually pronounced “sock” and sometimes called an information security operations center, or ISOC—is an in-house or outsourced team of IT security professionals dedicated to monitoring an organization’s entire IT infrastructure 24x7. Its mission is to detect, analyze and respond to security incidents in real-time. This orchestration of cybersecurity functions allows the SOC team to maintain vigilance over the organization’s networks, systems and applications and ensures a proactive defense posture against <a href="https://www.ibm.com/topics/security-operations-center">cyber threats</a>. A ‘<a href="https://www.paloaltonetworks.co.uk/cyberpedia/soc-as-a-service">SOC-as-a-service</a>’ (SOCaaS) is a cloud-based subscription model for managed threat detection and response.</p> <p>What are my expriences? What things do I suggest people look into, to help them work towards a path in a SOC environment?</p> <p>As I have mentioned before, when I first starting working in SOC, I found it hard initially. I found it challenging because I was worried about reporting something as benign, when it was in actuality a piece of malware. To combat this, I talked to some of the SOC management to learn more about the investigations I can do, I also refreshed my knowledge and the playbooks that are in place for the SOC - and I was assured that I could go to management if I was unsure of anything while on shift. I personally found that refresing my memory of the playbooks helped me the most, becuase reading is a learning format that works well for me - and I was able to have these playbooks open whilst I was on shift.</p> <p>It may sound obvious, but learning and understanding common networking protcols and their flavours such as HTTP/HTTPS, SMB, FTP, DNS, TCP and SSH to name a few would help to give more context to the activty you see. Knowing what default ports are associtaed with each of these protcols will help, but this is not essential for understanding, and being a competant analyst. Remember, when you are threat hunting, you have a scope to keep in mind when you are looking for suspicious activty - so keep this in mind when you are looking for unexpected activity on the network. It is easy to lose sight and dive down a rabbit hole of trying to understand a nuance of a particular network without context. I personally find it it helpful to have the scope and expected client outcomes written down on a piece of paper next to me.</p> <p>A lot of the time, unexpected activity that makes it’s way into a SOC queue could be the result of a pentest. As such, it is a good idea to keep in mind some of the indicators that would be visible in network traffic. For example, Nmap, whch can be run as a standalone program, but is most-commonly pre-packaged amongst OS’ such as Kali, has a default HTTP user agent (as of writing) of ‘Mozilla/5.0 (compatible; Nmap Scripting Engine; https://nmap.org/book/nse.html)’. Searching for this string in logs sometimes yields results. Searching for default user agents or even URIs as indicators may not always be effective - because in most cases, these default values can be changed by a potential attacker with little effort. It is always best to do your research and learn as much as you can before embarking on a journey like this.</p> <p>To summarise, I feel that you need to have an inqusitive mind in order to succeed in a role that requires you to work in a SOC. There will be a lot of things that you do not understand when starting out, and that’s okay. I’ve been lucky enough to have a very supportive team around me in my early days, that I can pose my ‘silly’ questions to. Having a team like this arround will help support your learning on the job, and hopefully inspire you to learn outside your role, as I did. I have a natural drive and desire to learn, which suits a SOC role because threats are constantly changing and in order to keep yourself up to date, you’ve got to be learning all the new ways threat actors are getting by in the wild.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="cybersec"/><category term="career"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This blog entry will update you all on what it has been like working in a SOC and a SOC-as-a-service capability for my employer. I will talk about my experiences and key takeaways. A SOC aims to improve an organization's threat detection, response and prevention capabilities by coordinating all cybersecurity technologies and operations.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">what is it like working in the Cyber Security industry?</title><link href="https://v-azza.github.io/blog/2023/working-in-cybersec/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="what is it like working in the Cyber Security industry?"/><published>2023-06-10T18:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-06-10T18:30:00+00:00</updated><id>https://v-azza.github.io/blog/2023/working-in-cybersec</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://v-azza.github.io/blog/2023/working-in-cybersec/"><![CDATA[<p>I often get asked about what it is like working in an industry like this. What is the easiest route into this profession? What degree must one do to get into this? Are there any certifications that you should look at before committing yourself to this line of work? This blog post will attempt to answer these questions and more.</p> <p>For the purposes of giving some perspective and before I start tackling the big questions - I’ll give a brief description of my professional life leading up to now. I am based in the United Kingdom and I have spent almost all of my life here. In terms of formal education, I’ve studied here from my early formative years all the way up to university level. I was born and raised in a small town in the middle of Lincolnshire, UK. Although it was quiet, there wasn’t really much in the way for exposure to the world of computing and cyber security. I remember my first sparks of interest in the world of computing came when I learnt Scratch for IT classes in high school. Scratch back then was very basic and although it had very simple functionality when compared to now - it was a great introduction to the word of programming for me. It introduced the concept of functions and loops to me, and what I really remember well was the fact that this software taught programming in ‘blocks’. You can think of each of these blocks as individual commands. Blocks are often easier to work with than text-based programming, as blocks do not need to be memorized like typed commands and syntax errors cannot occur - thus it is well-suited for learning for young children.</p> <p>I didn’t immediately seek formal education but when I eventually left my hometown - I didn’t choose to study a degree in an information security. I chose to study a degree in Aerospace Engineering. Although this doesn’t seem to immediately sound like it’s related to Cyber Security, there were a lot of fundamental skills I learnt during that course which have helped me in my career sp far. Some of those things are Mathematics, Physics, Programming (Python, MatLab), Presentation skills and Lab work. I spent 4 years at university and ultimately got a Master’s degree. I did some odd jobs during this time which included a stint as a brand representative for the UK’s national rail operator and a large multinational engineering company. I also worked in an office-based marketing role for a large multinational furniture retailer.</p> <p>After I graduated, I was lucky enough to have received an offer to work for one of the “Big Four” accountancy companies as a Cyber Security Consultant during the end of my second year of university. I then decided to start my professional career there. Early on, I was able to engage with C-suite individuals about their cyber security concerns in their businesses. Sometimes, I did feel very overwhelmed and out of my depth - however there was enough expertise on hand for me to find a leader or a subject matter expert (SME) to help answer any technical questions I had. For future engagement, I decided to combat this fear and feeling by shadowing senior leaders in my own time and promising myself I would record issues or subjects that I did not know about during the working day, to then research in my own time at home. Later on in my work with the company I had honed my skills and learnt that I wanted to strike the perfect balance between consulting clients on their Cyber Risk in general, as well as being able to dive into the technical detail with stakeholders if necessary. Looking back, I owe a lot to that company as they had supported me through some very difficult personal issues in my life and they had supported my learning and allowed me to gain cyber security certifications which benefit my development and work to this day.</p> <p>As I write this I now work for a company who is a market leader in Cyber Defence and Automated response. The company prides itself in it’s product offering which is an AI-driven tool which treats a corporate network much like the human body’s immune system. Much like the body’s immune system - it adapts it’s response and alerting of events based on common network behaviours for devices (the network being the human body in this case). I’ve been working in their SOC service offering from the start and this has been my first experience working in a SOC environment. I’ve found it to be a very significant learning experience as I have had the opportunity to have assessed a huge range of customer’s environments in such a short space of time. I am lucky to have worked in a place like this because I’ve had ample opportunities to upskill outside of work. For example, I have had the chance to learn how to develop and build my own website from scratch after working here. Not only am I able to all of the above, I am able to upskill when it comes to consultancy. I have been given the chance to engage with clients throughout the several stages of a product offering. Starting with the inital scoping, and any questions they have about the product itself, and how it works - all the way to the final stages of implementation and any questions around how the system will interact with current security solutions for example.</p> <p>The moral of the story is that absolutely anyone can get into this field! I mean that in the most absolute way possible. In my career so far in the cyber security industry, I have worked with people who’s backgrounds are from: biology, law, medicine and art, to name only a few. Long story short, you really DO NOT need to have a formal education in information technology, cyber security, or even any related formal qualification. You can get started with nothing more than a strong analytic drive, an attention for detail and a keen interest in learning complex topics. A lot of the concepts and ideas that makes a good cyber security analyst, for example can be self-taught. In my case, I have self-taught myself general web design, HTML, CSS and Javascript - all to aid me in building this website.</p> <p>In the future I would like to work in the public sector. I don’t know what form this will take or whether I will still be interested in doing this as much as I am now - but I would like to get a feeling for how security in the public sector works. I would also like to work on developing my learning, and building on the qualifications and certifications I already hold. I already hold SSCP, I would like to get CISSP, for example.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="cybersec"/><category term="career"/><category term="me"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I get asked a lot about what it is like working in the Cyber Security industry. It has it's ups and downs but generally, I love it. This blog post will detail my Cyber Security career up until this point, I will talk about the challeneges I've faced, and any other bits of important information that I feel you should know. There is no one agreed way to get into this industry, so click to learn more about my career journey leading to now.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">my useful software picks for 2023</title><link href="https://v-azza.github.io/blog/2023/software/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="my useful software picks for 2023"/><published>2023-02-24T12:39:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-02-24T12:39:00+00:00</updated><id>https://v-azza.github.io/blog/2023/software</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://v-azza.github.io/blog/2023/software/"><![CDATA[<p>Whether you are working in the Cyber Security industry, or you are just keen to learn more about software that can help make your life easier - or boost your productivity, you’re in the right place! This blog post will detail the pieces of software that has supported me throughout my professional career and have helped me surf the web in a secure and enjoyable way. Most of the pieces of software I will list below will be easily searchable through your favourite search engine and I will include links as much as I can. All this information is accurate as of February 2023.</p> <h3 id="1-ublock-origin">1. Ublock Origin</h3> <p>Given the target audience for this website - this might be a no-brainer. Ublock Origin is a Free, open-source ad blocker which is lightweight and works very well for almost any website.</p> <p>This is an absolute nescessity when surfing the web, regardless of the web browser you use. It helps that this browser extension is widely available in most web browsers add-ons/extensions’ store. It not only blocks ads on webpages throughout the internet, it also blocks ads from services such as Youtube, and as of right now (Feb 2023) video streaming services such as ITV Hub.</p> <h3 id="2-decentraleyes">2. Decentraleyes</h3> <p>Decentraleyes is another extension for all major web browsers, which promises to protect you against content tracking. Its primary task is to block connections to major CDNs such as Facebook, Cloudflare and Google (for privacy and anti-tracking purposes), and serve popular web libraries (such as JQuery and AngularJS) locally on the user’s machine.</p> <p>It’s worth keeping in mind however, using Decentraleyes in particular may break some desired functionality in some wesbites, for example - some CAPTCHAs/human verification tools will be broken using this, as some of them use the Cloudflare CDN to handle human verification requests. However, this is easily handled by using the menu in the extension to disbale Decentraleyes for the page you want to access.</p> <h3 id="3-rufus">3. Rufus</h3> <p>Rufus is a utility that helps you format and create bootable USB flash drives, such as USB keys/pendrives, memory sticks, etc. I’ve personally found this piece of software invaluable on the occasion I have to write an .iso image to a USB drive.</p> <h3 id="4-obs-studio">4. OBS Studio</h3> <p>OBS for short, is a widely-known streaming and content-creation software that is primarily used for video recording and online streaming. There isn’t really much to say about this piece of software as it is very easy to set up and use, and it does exactly what it says on the tin, for free.</p> <p>I’ve used this on occasion when I want to stream some content easily and quickly to my friends. I haven’t really used this much for video recording but it is very easy to set up with most cameras. It is free and open source.</p> <h3 id="5-microsoft-visual-studio-code">5. Microsoft Visual Studio Code</h3> <p>Yes, I can already hear you berating me. ‘Vaz, this isn’t truely open source!’ ‘Vaz this isn’t like all of the others you’ve mentioned thus far, it’s made by Microsoft! They’re evil!’ And yes, I do hear you. However this is where my personal preference comes into play and I really do think that this is a very powerful piece of software not just for programming but also for taking notes for example.</p> <p>It not only has a wide compatabilty and flexibilty regarding programming languages - it also boasts a large library of extensions which fill the gaps and allows it to be a very useful tool in my arsenal.</p> <h3 id="6-netlify">6. Netlify</h3> <p>You could argue that Netlify doesn’t belong on this list, and I’d be inclined to agree with you. Netlify is a platform for building websites, e-commerce stores and web applications. The reason I include Netlify in this list is because this service has been instrumental in helping me getting this site up and running, by streamlining the process of setting up the backend with zero financial input from me (as of this post). This website has been built and deployed using next.js and starting from one of their templates, I was able to build the site you see before you from this template. With this I am able to deploy my site from Github, and I am able to manage and edit my site from a central private repository from my GitHub account.</p> <p>Their starter plan is free and includes (as of this post) 100GB of bandwidth a month and 300 build minutes a month. I have never hit either limit and it is more than necessary to allow me to build out this site at my own pace. I have my partner to thank for introducing me to this platform, as she was using it during a coding course she was doing and introduced me to it - and it has been invaluable for me and this website.</p> <h3 id="7-pfsense">7. Pfsense</h3> <p>Pfsense is a leading open-source driven firewall, router, and VPN solution for network edge and cloud secure networking. I have it deployed on my home network, and it has been running for several years now, with little to no input or interventions needed from me. Of course a home network is nothing like the SLA-driven interests of running a business network where downtime is costly and must be avoided as much possible, but much like this website it has served as a learning platform.</p> <p>Setting this up and using this for my home network has let me learn more about IP subnetting, OpenVPN, network IDS/IPS (Snort) and networking in general. I have to admit, I was initially intimidated with the setup process and I was very concerned about the power usage. Namely, the amount it would add to my electricity bill - but I was smart in the selection of the components and I built a system designed to be used in the way a router should, with plenty of processing overhead for IDS/IPS capability.</p> <h3 id="8-steam">8. Steam</h3> <p>If you’re a gamer, and you have a PC that’s capable of playing games - Steam will naturally be one of the pieces of software that pops into the mind for a lot of people. That’s because the platform has been a steadfast constant for almost every PC gamer for a very long time. The steam game catalogue is vast and spans several hundred different genres. New releases are always being added, so you can always expect AAA games that are released on PC as a platform will likely be available on steam. For the retro-gamers out there, there also is a lot of games to choose from - and Steam consistently hold sales throughout the year with discounts ranging from 30 to 90% off!</p> <p>You might notice that Steam and it’s PC client for example, is proprietary software. However, I’ve included this in my list because I feel that this organsiation has taken significant strides in making gaming accessible to all, which benefits all of us - gamer or not. For example, as of the writing of this article, the Steam Deck has been out for almost a year (25th February 2022) and it has really shaken up the gaming industry, especially the handheld gaming industry. The Steam Deck is a portable handheld gaming PC that runs a modified version of the Arch Linux operating system, called SteamOS. Before Valve attempted this it could be argued that gaming on Linux was more than just a nuisance. I really do believe that this step of mass-producing a Linux-based handheld gaming device has accelerated the rate by which game developers create games for the Linux operating system, which I believe benefits all gamers. Time will only tell if all this work translates to more Linux-based games and more of a focus on gaming for Linux in general. In my about page, I’ve listed some of the games I am playing right now. Check the page out if you’re interested!</p> <h3 id="9-password-managers-i-currently-use-dashlane">9. Password Managers (I currently use Dashlane)</h3> <p>I highly recommend the use of a password manager. The NCSC in the United Kingdom says that the use of a password manager is beneficial because:</p> <ol> <li>You can synchronise your passwords across your different devices, making it easier to log on, wherever you are, and whatever you’re using. You can do this by easily copy and pasting the password from the app you choose to use, without ever having to remember a large amount of passwords - just one “Master Password”.</li> <li>It can help spot fake websites, which will protect you from phishing attacks.</li> <li>It can let you know if you’re re-using the same password across different accounts.</li> <li>It can notify you if your password appears within a known data breach so you know if you need to change it.</li> <li>It can work across platforms, so you could (for example) use a single password manager that would work for your iPhone and your Windows desktop.</li> </ol> <p>You can read more about the benefits of using a solution like this, in this really helpful NCSC article. You’ve probably already noticed that I use a non-open source solution for my password manager. But if you want something open-source and free, I would highly recommend KeePass.</p> <p>I currently use Dashlane and I have been doing so for more than 7 years. It works well for me and so long as a data breach on the level and severity as the one from LastPass doesn’t occur with Dashlane, I will keep using it as apposed to offline FOSS solutions for now.</p> <h3 id="10-signal">10. Signal</h3> <p>Signal is an end-to-end-encrypted instant messaging and SMS app. Users can send direct or group messages, photos, and voice messages across multiple devices. The key advantage that it offers over similar apps (such as Whatsapp, iMessage and Telegram, for example) is a strong focus on security and privacy. Some of the reasons why you should swtich to a secure end-to-end encrypted messaging app such as Signal is:</p> <ol> <li>End-to-end-encryption: When two or more Signal users start a conversation, they can use end-to-end encryption. This means that no intermediaries - not even at Signal HQ - can read your conversation.</li> <li>Open-source code: Open-sourced code lets security analysts around the world test and examine the app’s inner workings to determine whether it’s secure. They can also report bugs to Signal’s developers so they can improve the app. There’s always a theoretical chance that they aren’t actually using the code they’ve published, but all in all, open-source code means Signal can be trusted to be highly secure.</li> <li>Non-profit status: Signal is a non-profit organization. This reduces the incentive for them to try to collect and profit from user data.</li> </ol> <p>Although I use Whatsapp, Signal and Telegram for messaging - I have found it personally very difficult to stop using Whatsapp for example, because so many of my family members and friends use Whatsapp so often.</p> <h3 id="11-the-tor-browser-or-orbot-for-mobile-devices">11. The Tor Browser (or Orbot for mobile devices)</h3> <p>The Tor Browser is the gold standard for privacy-focused web browsing and .onion routing. You may use this as your regular web browser if you choose, but be prepared for slow-load times as your traffic is heavily encrypted (more so than normal HTTPS) and sent over the Tor network. The use of Tor, and the Tor Network is highly contentious as it has been commonly associated with cyber criminality, organised crime and the global drug trade. However, there are legitimate uses for Tor in areas of the world where the supression of the media is rampant. For example, journalists use Tor to communicate more safely with whistleblowers and dissidents, and non-governmental organizations (NGOs) use Tor to allow their workers to connect to their home website while they’re in a foreign country - without notifying everybody nearby that they’re working with that organization.</p> <p>If you want to route all your trafic from your mobile device through the Tor network, you can use Orbot which is available on both Android and iOS. There are options to force all network traffic through Tor, and to launch on startup, for those who are extra-privacy focused.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="software"/><category term="code"/><category term="cybersec"/><category term="tips"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[My top picks for applications and software that I use all the time. Some of these picks help boost your privacy online.]]></summary></entry></feed>